Guide to the Charles K. Bradsher Papers, 1951-1997
Duke University. University Archives
Charles K. Bradsher papers 1951-1997
Duke University. University Archives
Bradsher, Charles Kilgo, 1912-2000.
1.8 linear feet Extent: 1,500 Items
Charles Kilgo Bradsher was a Class of 1933 Duke alum and a Duke professor in the Chemistry Department from 1939-1979. His collection includes personal and departmental materials, especially concerning the Chemistry Department, the Gross-Edens Affair.
UA.29.02.0115
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Charles K. Bradsher Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1996, 2000-2001.
Biographical Note
Charles Kilgo Bradsher grew up in Petersburg, VA before receiving his B.A. from Duke in 1933, and his M.A. and Ph.D. from Harvard University in 1935 and 1937, respectively. He chaired the Department of Chemistry at Duke from 1965 to 1970 and also became the first director of the department's Chemistry for Executives program. In 1979, he became professor emeritus. Among his honors include the North Carolina Institute of Chemists' North Carolina Chemist Award for 1980, the Georgia Section American Chemical Society Herty Medal in 1987 and the Council for Chemical Research Malcolm El Pruitt Award for 1995. He died in 2000 at the age of 88.
Collection Overview
Collection includes personal and departmental materials concerning the history and faculty of the Department of Chemistry and the teaching of chemistry, the Gross-Edens Affair, long range planning, and research. Contains correspondence with Paul Gross concerning the Gross-Edens affair and documents regarding faculty promotions which should remain confidential. Replaced folder labels and discarded packet of departmental receipts for processing.
Subject Headings
Bradsher, Charles Kilgo, 1912-2000; Chemistry -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- North Carolina -- Durham; Duke University. Dept. of Chemistry; Duke University. Dept. of Chemistry -- Faculty; Edens, Arthur Hollis, 1901-; Gross, Paul Magnus, 1895-1986
Related Material
Gross (Paul M.) Papers, 1939-1979.
University Archives. Duke University.
Bigelow (Lucius A.) Papers, 1915-1973.
University Archives. Duke University.
Hobbs (Marcus E.) Papers, 1935-1980.
University Archives. Duke Archives.
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Bradsher Curriculum Vitae, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Chemistry Department Memoranda and Documents, 1970-1990 (Box 1)
  - North Carolina Institute of Chemists - Chemist of the Year, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Chemistry Newsletter, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Marsha (Box 1)
  - Gross Chemistry Building. Planning. Speeches (Box 1)
  - Alumni Departmental (Box 1)
  - Sabbatical Leave, 1959-1965 (Box 1)
  - Phi Beta Kappa by Departments, 1981-1992 (Box 1)
  - Chemistry 323, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Lectures, Chemistry 350 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1970-1997 (Box 1)
  - United Way, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Personnel Files - RESTRICTED (Box 1)
  - Staff Benefits (Box 1)
  - Screening Agreement (Box 1)
  - Council on the Gordon Research Conferences, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - Merck Sharp and Dohme (Box 1)
  - Terry Sanford Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Space Committee (Box 1)
  - Graduate School Memoranda (Box 1)
  - Bradsher: "Reactions of Some B-Naphthoquinones" (Box 1)
  - Personnel Files and Nominations - RESTRICTED (Box 1)
  - American Cyanamid (Box 1)
  - Herty Medal (Box 1)
  - Fullbright Fellowships (Box 1)
  - Netherlands Corresondence (Box 1)
  - N.S.F. Postdoctoral Fellowship, 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - Personal Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Duke Correspondence While in Zurich, Switzerland, 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - Inter-University Committee for Economic Research on the South. (Box 2)
  - Conference, Oct. 1964 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Virginia. The Joe Adams Fellowship Fund, 1977, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Brown, Frances Campbell. Correspondence, 1951-1994 (Box 2)
  - Quail Roost Conference Report, 1973 [Department of Chemistry review?] (Box 2)
  - Gross-Edens Matter, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Gross Chemistry Lab. Origins and dedication, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Chemistry Department history (Box 2)
  - Hobbs, Marcus E., 1982-1989 (Box 2)
  - Doxa [International Fuels Corp.] Proposal, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Planning, Long-Range, [University committee on] - Teaching, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Hauser, Charles Roy. Biography (Box 2)
  - Lochmueller, Charles H., 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - Dr. Bradsher. The John W. Watson Memorial Lectureship, 1966. (Box 2)
  - Vosburg Conference Room Committee, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Saylor, J.H.- Correspondence, [1964-1965] (Box 2)
  - General correspondence, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Paul Gross Correspondence, 1960 (Box 2)
  - American Chemical Society Meeting Attendance, 1953-1966 (Box 2)